This morning, well, this morning I was at the earlier מנין minyan
at five.
It was my mother's יארצייט Yahrzeit so I led some of the
דאוונן, davening, so I wanted to dedicate today's דף daf in her
memory, חנה בת מרדכי אליעזר Chana bas Mordechai Eliezer נשמתה. nishmasa.
And yeah, so let's let's get started. So we are on the
top of ע"ד עמוד א' Ayin Daled Amud Aleph and we have
been discussing this issue about the hanging limbs from an animal when
you שחט shecht the animal. So similar to the arm that's protruding
from the fetus where where we've said that when you שחט shecht
the animal that arm is forbidden, either because the שחיטה shechitah doesn't
apply to it or based on the verse of בשר בשדה טרפה.
basar basadeh tereifah. We've now said the same about a hanging limb
when the animal is שחטed, shecht that it cannot be eaten. But
although we quoted the verse בשר בשדה טרפה, basar basadeh tereifah, the
גמרא Gemara here says אין בהם אלא מצות פרוש בלבד. ein bahem
ella mitzvas poresh bilvad. It's only some, you know, מצות פרוש בלבד,
mitzvas poresh bilvad, it's only a מצות פרוש, mitzvas poresh it's not
really forbidden. Now what does that mean? So most understand, רש"י ותוספות
Rashi and Tosafot understand that that means that it's only rabbinic. That
even though the protruding limb of the fetus might be is a
biblical problem, this is only a rabbinic problem, which is funny because
it quoted a verse and it put it in the exact same
category as the fetus, but that's what רש"י ותוספות Rashi and Tosafot
says, that tends to be the standard explanation. Interestingly, the רמב"ם Rambam
understands that this phrase אין בהם אלא מצות פרוש בלבד ein bahem
ella mitzvas poresh bilvad applies equally to the dangling limb and the
limb of the fetus. And that even though we're learning it out
from this verse about בשר בשדה טרפה, basar basadeh tereifah, that it
does not carry the same weight as a biblical prohibition. It's somehow
the תורה's Torah telling us מצות פרוש mitzvas poresh, is at the
biblical level. The תורה's Torah telling us it's not appropriate to eat
or don't eat it, but not with the weight of a negative
prohibition. So for example, what is the story if you eat this
dangling limb or the protruding limb of the fetus? So the גמרא
Gemara is about to say when you eat the dangling limb, you
don't get מלקות. malkos. What about when you eat the limb of
the fetus? So some ראשונים Rishonim say you do get מלקות, malkos,
either because you've transgressed בשר בשדה טרפה basar basadeh tereifah or the
ראב"ד Ra'avad takes the earlier discussion of the גמרא Gemara very seriously,
and he says you could get מלקות malkos for eating a טרפה.
treifah. It's like a טרפה. treifah. An act of שחיטה shechitah was
done, it wasn't effective, and he would even say you would get
מלקות malkos for a טרפה. treifah. But the רמב"ם's Rambam approach is
to say there's really not a difference between the dangling limb and
the limb of the fetus, they're both maybe biblical but they're not
deserving of מלקות, malkos, they're not the same weight as the literal
prohibition. So anyway, that is what was just said about the dangling
limb and as a result, of course, says the גמרא, Gemara, if
it's not that forbidden, you're not, you know, even though you can't
eat it, you're certainly not going to treat it as a נבלה
neveilah and have טומאת נבלה. tumat neveilah. Certainly we'll say the שחיטה
shechitah was effective enough that it does not have, that it's like
more like a טרפה treifah than a נבלה, neveilah, which was the
discussion yesterday.
Just so I understand, so נבלה neveilah and טרפה, treifah, the same
punishment applies if you eat it?
Yeah, they're different לאוין, lavin, but they're both מלקות. malkos. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says let's
continue. Now יתיב רב יוסף קמיה דרב הונא, Yosiv Rav Yosef kamei
d'Rav Huna, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef was sitting in front of
רב הונא, Rav Huna, ויתיב וקאמר, veyosiv veka'amar, and he was sitting
and saying, this is what רב יוסף Rav Yosef was saying: אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, so רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda said in the name of רב, Rav, אכלו לזה לוקה.
achalo l'zeh lokeh. If you eat it, you do get מלקות. malkos.
Okay, does this sound to be like this case of the dangling
limb? Now it's interesting because if you remember yesterday, it was exactly
רב יוסף Rav Yosef that said מצות פרוש בלבד, mitzvas poresh bilvad,
or he quoted the אמורא Amora who said מצות פרוש mitzvas poresh
בלבד, bilvad, and here he's saying you get מלקות. malkos. But the
story isn't over. So אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן, amar lei hahu me-rabbanan,
so one of the רבנן Rabbanan that was sitting there, an anonymous
person, certainly not of the stature of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, but
some, one of the other people who was there in the presence
of רב הונא, Rav Huna, so said: לא תציתו ליה, lo tatzisu
lei, don't listen to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. הכי אמר רב יצחק
בר שמואל בר מרתא משמיה דרב, hachi amar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel
bar Marta mishmei d'Rav, here is another tradition in the name of
רב, Rav, אכלו לזה אינו לוקה. achalo l'zeh eino lokeh.
If you eat this, you don't get מלקות, malkos, because again presumably
it's only this מצות פרוש, mitzvas poresh, this case of the dangling
limb. So אמר ליה רב הונא, amar lei Rav Huna, so רב
הונא Rav Huna said to him: אנן אמאן נסמוך. anan amai nishmoch.
Who should we rely on? The tradition that רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said that you do get מלקות malkos in the name of רב,
Rav, or the tradition of this anonymous רב Rav who said in
the name of רב Rav that says you don't get מלקות? malkos?
So he was sort of weighing them equally. So אהדרי רב יוסף
לאפיה. ahadrei Rav Yosef l'appei. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef turned his
face around, like he turned his back to רב הונא. Rav Huna.
He was very offended. So he was offended that he was considering
relying on the other opinion, you know, especially this nobody sort of
said it.
And not only that as we'll see, he was offended because he
felt that he was misunderstood. Why was he misunderstood? Here's what he
said. He said אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said to רב
הונא, Rav Huna, מאי קשיא, mai kashya, what's your difficulty? Why are
you thinking that these are contradictory traditions? כי אמרי אנא, ki amri
ana, when I said in the name of רב Rav you get
מלקות, malkos, במיתה, b'misa,
I meant when the animal died, and then you had the dangling
limb, and what did we say happens when the animal dies with
the dangling limb? It's considered like the limb fell off and it's
אבר מן החי, ever min hachai, דאחוזי ניפול, d'ahosei nipel, it makes
it like the limb fell off and in that case you get
מלקות malkos for אבר מן החי ever min hachai from the dangling
limb. I wasn't talking about שחטing shecht it, I was talking about
when the animal died and it's an אבר מן החי ever min
hachai issue. כי אמר איהו, ki amar ihu, the other tradition in
the name of רב Rav that this other person said, בשחיטה, bishchitah,
that's when the... It was שחיטה shechted דאינו עושה ניפול d'eino osei
nifol
that it does not make the limb like אבר מן החי ever
min hachay and not only that the שחיטה shechitah does apply to
the limb and that you don't get lashes and it works it's
this מצות פרישה בלבד. mitzvas prosh bilvad. Okay so that clarified and
that makes the תוספות Tosfos consistent with what he said yesterday. Yes.
Yeah I'm troubled by this turning his back that רש"י Rashi says
בכעס. b'kaas. Right. If he had a tradition saying the opposite the
whole גמרא Gemara is full of debate. Why should he be why
how can he be angry for having a tradition?
It seems like he was angry for two reasons. Right it seems
like he's no no so he was angry. It seems he was
angry for two reasons. One reason is because maybe because you know
גמרא Gemara consistently does not say the name of the other of
his of his opponent here right ההוא מרבנן Hahu me-Rabbanan ההוא hahu
and so on. So presumably it was somebody of no real stature.
So he might have felt number one the very fact that רב
הונא Rav Huna is giving equal weight to what you know my
position and his this is somebody of no stature and so on.
That might be or somebody of I understand.
So that's one thing. I wouldn't go there because well for example
the whole מסכת עדיות masechet Eduyos you know what's profound about that
מסכת masechet which is you know right after the rabbis had to
regroup after the חורבן הבית Churban haBayis and יבנה Yavneh they took
all these testimonies was a lot of people that were of essentially
nobodies had no stature but had traditions and they and they and
that was taken seriously. Right. So the other the more reason it
seems why he was offended is is because he felt that רב
הונא Rav Huna was weighing the two and didn't even sort of
turn to him for clarification. So it was an ego thing. Yeah
well he said essentially why you all of a sudden like you
know trying to decide between and you're assuming that my tradition is
in conflict why don't you even ask me for like clarification. You
know that seems to be from the גמרא Gemara it sounded like
he was offended that רב הונא Rav Huna assumed that it was
a that he was possibly wrong and contradictory rather than asking for
clarification. That's what it seems like.
If the same thing had been said by a well-known and highly
respected רב. rav.
Then maybe he wouldn't have been as offended but that's my read
of it. That's not in the גמרא. Gemara. In the גמרא Gemara
what it explicitly says is he says why do you think there's
a problem right you know we're not contradicting so it seems like
maybe he was just more concerned that that there's an assumption that
he might be wrong rather than first inquiring for clarification.
Just so I understand. Yeah. What the גמרא Gemara just said. So
so basically so in the end of the day he's saying that
the dangling limb is as much of a נבלה neveilah as the
rest of the animal.
If you no no no if it dies no it's a נבלה.
neveilah. The animal is נבלה neveilah and the limb is an אבר
מן החי. ever min hachay. That's what עושה ניפול osei nifol oh
okay okay.
But the same punishment.
Well yeah except the difference would be אבר מן החי ever min
hachay is אסור assur to בני נח Bnei Noach and so on
but there are other implications. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. אמר רבא Amar Rava so says רבא
Rava מנא מיוסף דאמרו רבנן minah m'yosaf d'amar Rabbanan where's this thing
from that the rabbis say מיתה עושה ניפול שחיטה אינה עושה ניפול.
misah osei nifol shechitah eino osei nifol. Exactly what we said with
the dangling limb if the animal dies it's like the limb fell
off and it's אבר מן החי ever min hachay and if it
was שחיטה shechted then it's actually not such a problem. It's prohibited
but it's not such a problem and it's not טמא tamei and
so on. That it's not like it fell off. דכתיב De'chsiv so
where's this from. מיתה עושה ניפול שחיטה אינה עושה misah osei nifol
shechitah eino osei דכתיב De'chsiv the פסוק pasuk says וכל אשר יפול
עליו מהם במותם. v'chol asher yipol alav meihem b'mosam.
This is talking about dead שרצים shratzim and whatever that they when
they're dead they fall on things and they make them טמא. tamei.
Anything that falls from them in their death. יטמא yitma it shall
become טמא. tamei. למיעוטי מאי lemuti mai so why does it say
when they're death. It already says מנבלתם mi-nivlatam earlier in the פסוק
pasuk from their carcasses. So why do you have to once again
say in their death. So למיעוטי מאי lemuti mai what is this
excluding. אילימא למיעוטי בחייהם Ilei de-lemuti b'chayeihem if they fall when they're
alive and they touch food בנבלתם נפקא bi-nivlatam nafka it says from
their carcasses. אלא שמע
מינה ela shema mina so the fact that it repeated במותם b'mosam
מיתה עושה ניפול ואין שחיטה עושה ניפול. misah osei nifol v'ein shechitah
osei nifol.
That some things that fall from them it's actually a creative read
of the פסוק. pasuk. It doesn't mean literally we would read the
פסוק pasuk אשר יפול מהם asher yipol meihem when one of them
falls on something but here it's reading the פסוק pasuk אשר יפול
מהם asher yipol meihem when something falls off of them a limb
falls off of them במותם b'mosam in their death it's like the
limb the dangling limb is considered as if it fell off of
them. So that's how when they die it's that עושה ניפול osei
nifol it's drawing on this פסוק pasuk יפול yipol it's like the
limb fell off of them. Okay שמע מינה מיתה עושה ניפול ואין
שחיטה עושה ניפול shema mina misah osei nifol v'ein shechitah osei nifol
but not שחיטה shechting them. So because it's במותם b'mosam only when
they die not when they not when they're שחיטה. shechted.
So but these things aren't שחיטה shechted though.
Well I know that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. אמר
ליה רב אדא בר אבא לרבא Amar lei Rav Ada bar Abba
l'Rava so רב אדא בר אבא Rav Ada bar Abba said to
רבא Rava והא קרא בשרצים כתיב veha k'ra b'shratzim ksiv it's talking
about these like שרצים shratzim and there's no שחיטה shechitah by שרצים
shratzim you know they're never כשר kosher so how can you say
it's contrasting death to
שחיטה. shechitah. So אמר ליה amar lei he said back to him
אינו עניין לשרצים דלאו בני שחיטה נינהו einu inyan l'shratzim d'lav bnei
shechitah ninhu you're right but if it's not relevant for שרצים shratzim
because there there's no meaning to contrast שחיטה shechitah to death because
there's no שחיטה shechitah by these שרצים shratzim but still the פסוק
pasuk that's emphasizing death and we understand it to be in contrast
to שחיטה shechitah תניהו עניין לבהמה t'neihu inyan l'beheimah
so use that teaching of contrasting death to שחיטה shechitah for animals.
suggested שחיטה shechita for a place where it is relevant, for animals,
for mammals and so on. Somebody there?
I don't know.
ודקא מיבעיא ליה, vedeka mibaia lei, the גמרא gemara says still, how
can you learn from במותם bemotam this idea that it's as if
the limb fell off? We need the word במותם bemotam to tell
me another principle of טומאה: tumah: כעין מיתה, ke-ein mitah, that they
only cause
טומאה tumah
when they are like the moment that they died. What does that
mean? לחים מטמאין יבשין אין מטמאין, lachim metamin yeveshin ein metamin,
that dead rodents or whatever only cause טומאה tumah when they are
still moist, as opposed to when they have
totally shriveled up and become desiccated. Exactly. So, and we learn it
from the word במותם. bemotam. It has to be like the moment
of death. So the גמרא gemara says תרי במותם כתיבי, trei bemotam
kesivi, it says במותם bemotam twice in the verse, one to teach
me that and the other to teach me the other thing. You
can check the verses. אמר רב חסדא. amar rav chisda. Okay, so
that's where we get the idea that a dangling limb when the
animal dies naturally, it's like it fell off and it's אבר מן
החי. eiver min hachai. When the animal is שחט, shachted, it's not
טמא, tamei, it's not אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. Still don't
eat it. That's this idea of מצות פרוש, mitzvas prosh,
whether that means דאורייתא de'oraisa without lashes or means דרבנן, derabanan, but
that's what you have.
No one will say you can eat this dangling limb?
No. The most the גמרא gemara will say is מצות פרוש. mitzvas
prosh. No one views it as still
part of the
animal because
it's still attached? Well, it's enough part of the animal that the
שחיטה shechita makes it not a נבלה. neveilah. It's enough part of
the animal that according to some ראשונים rishonim it's only a דרבנן
derabanan problem, but it's not attached enough that the שחיטה shechita works
for it, like the limb of the fetus. And
what defines dangling? That I don't know. I think the basic definition
is that the majority, how you exactly define majority, but that the
majority is disconnected. Yes.
What is a literal translation of אבר מן החי? eiver min hachai?
A limb from a live animal. אבר eiver is a limb from
the live animal. Okay. So now the גמרא gemara says like this,
אמר רב חסדא, amar rav chisda, says רב חסדא, rav chisda, מחלוקת
באבר דעובר חי. machlokes be-eiver de-ubar chai. We're talking about the limb
of a live
fetus and then you שחט shacht the mother and what's the status
of that limb? Is it a נבלה, neveilah, is it a טריפה,
treifa, and so on? אבל באבר דעובר מת, aval be-eiver de-ubar meis,
if it's a dead fetus. Now remember if it's a dead fetus
and it's in the mother's womb and you שחט shacht the mother,
you can eat the fetus. It's still considered like a part of
the mother. But let's say you have a limb protruding from the
womb and the fetus has died and you שחט shacht the mother.
What's the status of that limb? So there he says דברי הכל
שחיטה עושה ניפול divrei hakol shechita osah nipul
because the thing it's attached to is already dead. That's already then
even though you שחט shachted it, then we will consider it like
the limb had fallen off and the limb actually will become אבר
מן החי. eiver min hachai. ורבא אמר, verava amar, and רבא rava
says no, כמחלוקת בזה
כך מחלוקת בזה. kemachlokes be-zeh kach machlokes be-zeh. I hear that the
fetus is dead, but nevertheless the only concept that we have that
when the animal dies it's like a limb fell off is when
it dies naturally. When שחט, shachted, it's never like the limb fell
off. Again, the biggest difference being you still can't eat this whether
it's the limb of the fetus or the dangling limb, you can't
eat it. The biggest issue here in the גמרא gemara is whether
it's like a נבלה neveilah or אבר מן החי eiver min hachai
for purposes of טומאה וטהרה. tumah ve-tahara. Okay? So with that we
end that point. Again, the questions about whether the שחיטה shechita worked
for it and is it a נבלה neveilah for טומאה tumah purposes
or is it more like a טריפה. treifa. But certainly the other
thing is that we see the issue about the fetus with the
arm out or the dangling limb when you שחט shacht the mother.
What's the nature of that prohibition? So the גמרא gemara has quoted
the verse ובשר בשדה טריפה u-vasar ba-sadeh treifah which some will say
that you'll even get lashes for the case of the fetus, either
for that or because it's like a טריפה. treifa. In case of
the dangling limb, there the גמרא gemara says מצות פרוש mitzvas prosh
which some understand it to mean a דרבנן, derabanan, but the רמב"ם
rambam understands that whether the dangling limb or the limb of the
fetus, it's biblical but it's not really the weight of a prohibition
and that's what it means מצות פרוש mitzvas prosh and you don't
get lashes. Okay, now we are going to finish this up. בן
שמונה חי. ben shemonah chai. If it is an eight-month-old baby and
you שחט shachted the mother, I'm sorry, and it was born. Excuse
me. Then the משנה mishna said that and you שחט shacht it,
the שחיטה shechita it doesn't help. It's still like a נבלה. neveilah.
It's not like a טריפה. treifa. Why? Because the גמרא's gemara assumption
that an eight-month-old baby is not viable, so it's more or less
as if it's already dead, so the שחיטה shechita is not going
to help it and it's going to remain a status of a
נבלה. neveilah.
Do they have the same gestation period as humans?
Oh, that is a good question and I'm sure everybody can now
get onto their Wikipedia, but I don't know. The גמרא, gemara, certainly
the משנה's mishna assuming that and assuming the same rules of whatever
of
eight-month-old versus nine-month-old. What were you going to say?
It assumes also to be more בדיוק, bediyuk, that it really is
the same nine
months.
What do you mean, one more time?
Just when we're learning about the שחיטה shechita course, the type of
stuff that you end up dealing with, the human fetuses, that we
assume it can be in a range of time that it's not
going to be born exactly at nine months, isn't
the סוגיא sugya
end up assuming that an animal is born exactly nine months later
and you can use that as a determination factor להלכה? le-halacha?
For what question?
I'm trying to remember where the נפקא מינות nafka minas were in
that section, but there were נפקא מינות nafka minas about whether or
not you could, when you had to guess. And you don't know
is this the same child of this mother.
Ah, okay. Interesting.
And in some questions you can use determination, oh no, he's only
eight months, eight and a half months, it can't be the same
child of this mother.
Got it. Interesting. All right. So let's take a look.
You introduced the idea of viability. Right. How do I know that?
How do I know? You're right, it hasn't been stated. I know
it from a lot of other places in the גמרא Gemara where
it speaks about how an eight-month-old baby is not considered viable and
you can't even move it on שבת Shabbos because it's מוקצה, muktzah,
no, it says it's כאבן. ke-even. So a born baby that only
gestated for eight months and not nine months, the גמרא Gemara assumes
it's going to die and won't even let the mother pick it
up to nurse it on שבת. Shabbos. Now we, of course, don't
follow that because we basically say, you know, either we say reality
has changed or we say our technology has changed and we know
how to sustain babies better, whatever. But yes, according to the גמרא
Gemara they completely assumed that an eight-month-old baby, there was no point
in even nursing them because they were just going to die.
At what point do they, does that after the גמרא? Gemara? No,
no, I mean at what point, how old does the baby have
to get to be considered viable?
It
has to be complete, it has to do a, it has to
finish medical school. Right,
that's the joke. Right, so anyway, but so how does one know
eight months?
Right,
so that's part of the question also, based, sometimes you do it
based on the characteristics and how it looks like when it's born.
That's also a way that you sort of get around these things
is you say that if it was viable even though it was
eight months, it was really a nine-month-old baby that was born early,
whatever, it's a whole lot of details. But anyway, yeah, right, so
anyway, so
let's go on. All right. והתניא, ve-hatanya, so says the גמרא, Gemara,
בן שמונה חי. ben shemonah chai. והתניא, ve-hatanya, says the גמרא, Gemara,
do we not teach in a ברייתא, Baraisa, בן שמונה חי יוכיח,
ben shemonah chai yochiach, שאף על פי שיש במינו שחיטה, she-af al
pi she-yesh bemino shechitah, אין
שחיטתו מטהרתו? ein shechitato meta'arato? So if you remember the גמרא, Gemara,
the issue in the משנה Mishnah was, where do we know this
idea that a טרפה treifah is not טמא? tamei? And it said,
well, because we should compare it to a non-kosher animal, you שחט
shecht it and it is טמא. tamei. So it tried to say,
well, it's different because at least this animal the שחיטה, shechitah, you
know, can work under other circumstances and therefore it's enough to make
it not טמא. tamei. So it said, well, what about an eight-month-old
baby? The שחיטה shechitah doesn't work there and if you, never works
by eight-month-old babies and when you שחט shecht it, it is still,
it's not טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara says, well, when you
שחט shecht it, it is טמא. tamei. So it says well, that's
אין במינו שחיטה, ein bemino shechitah, they considered the eight-month-old baby as
if it was its own מין, min, like its own species, and
since that מין min never has שחיטה, shechitah, it's just like a
non-kosher animal and that's why even when you שחט shecht it, it
remains טמא. tamei. So let's take a look. The ברייתא, Baraisa, however,
assumes that it is not considered to be its own species. So
let's take a look at the ברייתא. Baraisa. והתניא, ve-hatanya, did we
not teach in a ברייתא, Baraisa, בן שמונה חי יוכיח, ben shemonah
chai yochiach,
an eight-month-old baby should prove that you can sometimes שחט shecht something
and it would still be טמא, tamei, שאף על פי שיש במינו
שחיטה, she-af al pi she-yesh bemino shechitah, although there are in its
species שחיטה, shechitah, because other animals you שחט shecht it works, אין
שחיטתו מטהרתו, ein shechitato meta'arato,
when you שחט shecht this, it still remains טמא. tamei. So the
same should be true about a טרפה. treifah. So אמר רב כהנא,
amar Rav Kahana, יש במינו שחיטה אגב אמו. yesh bemino shechitah agav
imo. No, the מין, min, again it's very funny, the species of
eight-month-old babies, there's never שחיטה shechitah by it, but there is שחיטה
shechitah when it's in its mother's womb when you שחט shecht the
mother. So sometimes שחיטה shechitah can be effective by it even though
when it's not done to it directly. So therefore, according to this
ברייתא, Baraisa, we're saying how can you say that when שחיטה shechitah
is relevant, the animal won't be טמא? tamei? שחיטה shechitah is relevant
to an eight-month-old baby because you could שחט shecht the mother and
the animal will still be טמא tamei when you שחט shecht it.
So the גמרא Gemara says, someone turns to that.
So we're saying that since you can שחט, shecht, no, I get
it now. Thank you. Yeah, since you can שחט shecht the mother
and the mother had a fetus inside of it,
therefore שחיטה shechitah is relevant and even though שחיטה shechitah is relevant,
when you שחט shecht the animal itself, it's טמא. tamei. So we
should say the same by a טרפה, treifah, that even though שחיטה
shechitah is relevant, when you שחט shecht it, it should be טמא.
tamei.
But if you שחט shecht the mother of an eight-month-old baby, you
don't know it's an eight-month, it could be a nine-month-old baby.
Whatever, don't worry about that, we're assuming in case you do. Okay.
ולתנא דידן, ve-letanna didan, so the גמרא Gemara says,
wait but I thought Michael's question was going to be, so in
the case of an eight-month-old baby that's not born, the שחיטה shechitah
of the mother makes the baby כשר, kosher, makes the fetus כשר.
kosher. In the case of an eight-month-old baby that's born prematurely, שחיטה
shechitah of that animal itself,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara is about to say, that that's
exactly the debate between our משנה Mishnah and the ברייתא, Baraisa, whether
you can even say that the שחיטה shechitah of the mother is
at all relevant to the fetus because on its own terms it's
not relevant. Right, right, so that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say.
So let's take a look. Yeah, and the other cases that you
provided which I think we would describe either funny-looking kids or offspring
that are born with anomalies. So if you had a fetus with
anomalies, which was
Yeah. Right. So you would then think that if you שחט shecht
*shechted* it after after its premature birth that it would not be
כשר *kosher*. Well, but if it was שחט shechted *shechted* in before
prior to that birth, would it be כשר *kosher*?
Right, so the answer is yes. Anything שחט shecht *shechted* in the
mother's womb alive, anomalies, טרפה *trefa*, eight months, whatever, is part of
the mother and is כשר *kosher*. The anomalies thing will come up
in the end here where we speak about when it's born with
a טרפה *trefa* actually is the issue the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* talks
about. So let's take a look. ותנא דידן מנא ליה *V'tana didan
minalei*, ותנא דידן *v'tana didan* our תנא *tana* that considers this to
be אין במינו שחיטה shechita *ein bemino shechita*. מינא דאימיה לא פריך
*Mina d'imei lo parich*, it says the species of the mother is
not relevant, it doesn't ask that question because what's relevant to the
mother is not for the infant for the fetus itself. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: ולהאי תנא דפרך טרפה דשחיטתה מטהרתה מנא ליה
*u'lehay tana deparich trefa de-shechitata metaharata minalei*. Now again remember, the whole
the larger context here is, how do we know that שחיטה shechita
*shechita* of a טרפה *trefa* makes the animal at least not cause
טומאה *tuma*, right, which is the הלכה *halacha*. If the animal dies,
a נבלה *nevela*, it does cause טומאה *tuma*. If you שחט shechted
*shecht* it and it's טרפה *trefa* even though you can't eat it,
it doesn't. So the משנה mishna. *Mishna* says, well, at least שחיטה
shechita *shechita* of a טרפה *trefa* is different because at least in
that species of animal שחיטה shechita *shechita* is relevant, so therefore it
should be effective enough to prevent it from becoming טמא *tamei*. So
the question is, does the case of the eight-month-old baby present a
counter-example? Because if you שחט shechted. *shecht* an eight-month-old baby, it's considered
like a נבלה *nevela* and it causes טומאה *tuma*. Is that a
counter-example? So according to our משנה mishna *Mishna*, it wasn't a counter-example
because our משנה mishna *Mishna* said that you consider that a species
unto itself, אין במינו שחיטה shechita *ein bemino shechita*, so שחיטה shechita
*shechita* is irrelevant for this species. So it's not a counter-example. We're
saying by טרפה *trefa* שחיטה shechita *shechita* in principle is relevant and
that's why it doesn't cause טומאה *tuma*. The ברייתא Baraisa, *braita* here
says that no, even though it's an eight-month-old baby, שחיטה shechita *shechita*
is in principle relevant to it because you could שחט shecht *shecht*
it through its mother, and therefore here's a counter-example, an animal which
שחיטה shechita *shechita* is relevant to and when you שחט shechting *shecht*
it, it still causes טומאה *tuma*. So why should טרפה *trefa* be
any different? So that's what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* asks. According to
this תנא *tana*, how do you know that by a טרפה *trefa*
when you שחט shecht *shecht* it,
it's not it remains not טמא *tamei*? מנא ליה *Minalei*, נפקא ליה
מדרב יהודה אמר רב *nafka lei mid'Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, from the
statement of רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* in the name of רב *Rav*.
דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב *D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, ואמרי לה
במתניתא תנא *v'amri lei be-matnita tana*, and some say we taught in
a ברייתא Baraisa, *braita*, אמר קרא *amar kra* the verse says: וכי
ימות מן הבהמה *v'chi yamut min ha-behema*, when one of the animals
dies that you can eat, it says if you touch its carcass
you are טמא *tamei*. So it's so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says:
מן הבהמה *min ha-behema*, מקצת בהמה מטמאה *miktzat behema metama*, only some
animals when they die cause טומאה *tuma* even כשר *kosher* animals, ומקצת
בהמה אינה מטמאה *u'miktzat behema einah metama*, some animals when they die
don't cause טומאה *tuma*. What is the difference? Not what type of
an animal it is, ואיזו זו *v'eizo zu*, it's how it died.
זו
טרפה ששחטה *Zo trefa she-shechata*, if we שחט shecht *shechted* it and
it's a טרפה *trefa* and you שחט shecht *shechted* it, then even
though it died, it does not cause טומאה *tuma*. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says we learn it from the verse. The verse
says when some of the animals, that's how we're reading it, die,
sometimes when an animal dies it causes טומאה *tuma*, sometimes it doesn't.
When doesn't it? Even if it's a טרפה *trefa* and as long
as you שחט shecht *shechted* it, it doesn't cause טומאה *tuma*.
I wouldn't use this for the metadelic case, but whatever. Okay. What
is a טרפה *trefa*?
A טרפה *trefa* is an animal with an internal injury that it's
going to die within a year.
Okay, so
גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says okay. בעי רב הושעיא *Ba'i Rav Oshaya*, רב הושעיא *Rav
Oshaya* asks the following question. So
this is a fun question which will also take us into the
next משנה mishna. *Mishna*. הושיט ידו למעי בהמה *Hoshit yado l'mei behema*,
a שוחט *shohet* stuck his hand into the mother's womb where there
was a fetus, ושחט *v'shachat*, and he שחט shecht *shechted* the fetus
inside the mother's womb. Okay, this fetus that doesn't need שחיטה shechita
*shechita*, you can do it through the שחיטה shechita *shechita* of the
mother, the question is it doesn't need שחיטה shechita *shechita* but will
שחיטה shechita *shechita* be meaningful to it while it's still in utero?
Okay, or at that stage it's not considered its own animal and
שחיטה shechita *shechita* it can't be meaningful to it. Is that possible?
I don't know. Okay, so ושחט בן תשעה חי מהו *v'shachat ben
tishah chai mahu*? תיבעי לרבי מאיר ותיבעי לרבנן *Tiba'i l'Rabbi Meir
v'tiba'i l'Rabbanan*.
You could ask this according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir*,
you can ask this according to the רבנן rabbanan *Rabbanan*, the debate
whether the שחיטה shechita *shechita* of the mother works for the infant,
which we're going to see in the coming up משנה mishna *Mishna*.
Until now we've been assuming the שחיטה shechita *shechita* of the mother
works for the infant, but actually רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
says it does not. But this question can go either way. תיבעי
לרבי מאיר *Tiba'i l'Rabbi Meir*, you can ask according to רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*, עד כאן לא קאמר רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
בן פקועה ben pakua. טעון שחיטה taun shechita. *ad kan lo ka'amar
Rabbi Meir ben pakua teun shechita*, until now רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* when he normally says that the בן פקועה ben pakua
*ben pakua*, which is a child like at birth forth, meaning when
you שחט shecht *shechted* the mother there was a fetus in utero,
he says that it requires שחיטה shechita *shechita* even though you שחט
shecht *shechted* the mother. הני מילי היכא דיצא לאויר העולם *Hani mili
heichi d'yatza l'avir ha-olam*, that after it comes after it's born or
not born after it's taken out of the mother's womb after you
שחט shecht *shecht* the mother. So once it's emerged into the world,
it's its own animal and it requires שחיטה shechita *shechita* and the
שחיטה shechita *shechita* of the mother didn't work for it. אבל במעי
אמו aval bimei imo *Aval b'mei imo*,
so therefore excuse me, the point is like this. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* says that this fetus in the mother's womb, the
שחיטה shechita, *shechita* of the mother doesn't work for it. So he
presumably is recognizing this fetus as much more sort of its own
entity because the שחיטה shechita *shechita* of the mother doesn't work for
it. Therefore according to him the logic would dictate that it's possible
that if you שחט shechted *shechted* it in utero it works, because
he even when it's in utero he sees it as
Maybe it's enough of its own entity so that when it's finally
comes out into the world then you can do a שחיטה shechita,
to it but not enough of its own entity that even in
utero שחיטה shechita, is meaningful.
But you're assuming that the fetus or the baby is born alive?
Yes.
Yes. Okay. And with that we're going to...
If the baby dies.
If the baby dies. If it's dead in utero then the שחיטה
shechita, of the mother would work. We're going to see that in
the next משנה. mishna Okay. So even though he says that it's
its own entity and you do a שחיטה shechita? to it הני
מילי היכא דאתא לאויר העולם. hani mili heichi deyata l'avir haolam. That's
you can do a שחיטה shechita, once it's really is fully its
own entity and it's come out into the world and it's a
full animal. אבל במעי אמו while it's still in utero it might
be enough of its own entity that the שחיטה shechita of the
mother doesn't work for it but לא שייכא ליה שחיטה lo shaycha
lei shechita but also if you stuck your hand in and did
שחיטה shechita that would also not be meaningful. It's not yet an
animal in its own right. That's one possibility. You could say it
doesn't work even according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir או דילמא o
dilma or go the opposite way. אפילו רבנן afilu rabbanan even the
רבנן rabbanan. that say the שחיטה shechita of the mother does work
for the fetus they're just maybe they're just saying that that is
a sufficient that's an alternative way to do a שחיטה shechita but
maybe you could also do a שחיטה shechita on the fetus itself.
ארבעה סימנים אכשר ליה רחמנא arba simanim achshar lei rachmana maybe the
Torah says there are four סימנים simanim you know because two סימנים
simanim with the trachea and the esophagus. So there are four סימנים
simanim to this animal and any two not really any two you
can't do one סימן siman of the mother and one סימן siman
of the fetus but either of the two sets will work. So
either you can use the שחיטה shechita of the mother to work
for it or its own שחיטה shchita to work for it. Okay.
So it raises the question is does the שחיטה shchita work? Can
this yet be considered in utero enough of its own animal that
the שחיטה will work for it?
Moving inside the technical impossibility of doing שחיטה in utero.
Right. Correct. This is all yeah. This is a thought experiment. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara, says אמר רב חנינא amar Rav Hanina so
רב חנינא Rav Hanina says תא שמע ta shma הרי שנולד טריפה
מן הבטן. harei shenolad trefah min habeten.
So the משנה mishna speaks about an animal that was born our
משנה mishna that was born a טריפה trefah right from the moment
it was born. From the moment it was born it was a
טריפה. trefah. ואי איתא ve'i ita and it says that that's a
case where it was never permissible to be eaten. That was the
case of our משנה. But if it's true that it's possible to
שחט shecht an animal in utero משכחת לה דהיתה לה שעת כושר
mishkachas lah dehayta lah sha'at kosher
there could be a moment before it was born before it became
a טריפה trefah assuming it became a טריפה trefah a minute before
it was born. So why does the משנה say that it never
could have been eaten? There was a moment it could have been
eaten. דאי בעי מעייל ידיה ושחט de'ei ba'ei me'ayel yadei veshachat you
could have שחט it in utero. So the משנה gives an example
of an animal that never had a moment that it was possible
to eat that was born with the as a טריפה. trefah. So
it says why did that never have a moment it could have
eaten if you could שחט it in utero? You could have שחט
it in utero before it became a טריפה. trefah. So the גמרא
Gemara is saying אמר ליה רבא amar lei Rava תני שנוצרה טריפה
מן הבטן. tani shenotzra trefah min habeten. No not just it was
born as a טריפה trefah it was conceived as a טריפה. trefah.
How do you know that? How do you know that it had
to because he says ומשכחת לה בבעלת חמש רגלים umishkachas lah bevalat
hamesh raglayim
because it has a birth defect. There you go David. So it
actually if it's born with five legs and and remember an extra
leg is like it's missing a leg. So a hind leg if
it's missing a hind leg it's a טריפה trefah so an extra
hind leg is a טריפה. trefah. So there it says that didn't
happen a minute before it was born. That happened that that happened
that that began from the moment of conception. So that animal never
could have been שחט. So it is theoretically possible you could שחט
an animal in utero and a certain type of an animal you
know never had a moment when it could have ever been eaten.
But I'm sure in a lung you know maybe that happened.
That maybe right but this you know not. So anyways now we
have this I think again this really fascinating little thing about the
שחיטה of the mother works for the fetus is it possible the
fetus at least can also have its own status in terms of
שחט it whether according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir or the רבנן.
Rabanan, I just also want to point out I don't know but
I just also want to point out it's unresolved that you know
sometimes like remember we discussed by טריפות trefas and the גמרות Gemaras
that speak a seem to be somewhat relevant to some of these
questions about the brain death controversy and so on. You know all
of these discussions you would think that they should be relevant in
conversations about like abortion right? You know I mean it seems very
much like a does this have its own status not have its
own status at this stage and so on. Surprisingly like this does
not come up in the conversation at all at least as of
my knowledge you know all these questions which seem very relevant about
to what degree is the fetus justified as a mother as viable
has its own status not its own status.
Is there also a conversation in the Orthodox world about abortion?
Yeah sure. I mean maybe maybe that they don't I mean maybe
they don't talk about it too much but there definitely is a
range of opinions about abortion.
There are opinions but...
Oh sure there are definitely different פוסקים poskim about it. I mean
it could be that the common you know the party line is
maybe follows more sort of the you know or I shouldn't say
follows but is more in line with also you know sort of
the Catholic Church approach about like how it's always אסור assur but
that's certainly what?
That's the political.
That's the political party line. Yeah but in terms of the actual
no there're definitely cases where people have what? Yeah רב ולדנברג Rav
Waldenberg was very lenient and ציץ אליעזר. Tzitz Eliezer. and about those
issues and even contemporary פוסקים *poskim* right now, I mean based on
situations,
you know, based on the severity of the situation and how developed
the child is or whatever, based on which פוסק *posek* somebody asks,
they can get different answers. So it’s not necessarily only one way.
I mean, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has ספקות *sfekot* with ארבעים יום
*arba'im yom* and ספקות *sfekot* issues.
Right. Okay, so we’re not giving a שיעור *shiur* on that right
now.
In the תשובות *teshuvot* they
don’t, to the best of my knowledge, they don’t discuss these גמרות
*Gemarot*. I mean, there are enough גמרות *Gemarot* about abortion with human
fetuses that they talk about. I don’t know, I could look, but
at least I do not remember that they directly pull in these
גמרות *Gemarot*. Okay.
Yeah, I want to go back to eight-month-old human babies. If it’s
a boy, do you do a ברית *bris*?
You don’t do a ברית *bris* on
שבת *Shabbos* because...
not on שבת *Shabbos*, but in every other respect...
Yes,
but largely nowadays we have basically made those הלכות *halachos* moot.
So has anybody said "this is wrong"?
They never say it that way. What they will say is נשתנו
הטבע *nishtanu hateva*. That is the politically correct way to say that
our science and our understanding of nature does not accord
with what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. So you could say the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* got it wrong, which the רמב"ם *Rambam* actually says.
The רמב"ם *Rambam* was not... did not have a problem saying חז"ל
*Chazal* weren’t scientists, so sometimes they had the same science as their
day. And
actually nowadays there will be people that will say the same thing.
But over hundreds of years, that was not the thing to say.
So the way they dealt with it is by saying our science,
our nature, our natural world has changed. But once they can allow
that our natural world is different for whatever reason, then that at
least allowed for them to talk about what the הלכה *halacha* now
will be.
So would the baby have a ברית *bris* then on שבת *Shabbos*
today,
if the baby’s
born the eighth month?
That I think probably still not, whether a שבת *Shabbos* ברית *bris*.
That I think still not, but pretty much for anything... What? Most
of the time he's premature and he's not ready yet for a
שבת *Shabbos* ברית *bris*.
But it could be...
In the eighth month it's a full...
Some women don't care to know.
That's an interesting question. I'd have to look at that. I'd have
to
look... Alright, let's move on. I'd have to look at that question.
I don't remember offhand about the שבת *Shabbos* ברית *bris*. Alright, וייטער
*veiter*. השוחט את הבהמה ומצא בה בן שמונה חי או מת *Hashochet
et habehema umatza ba ben shmona chai o met*, pay attention. השוחט
את הבהמה ומצא בה בן שמונה חי או מת *Hashochet et habehema
umatza ba ben shmona chai o met*. So now we... the earlier
debate... Okay, people, we’re behind and I need your focus. No side
conversations. Okay, so I will wait. Thank you. Okay, so we had
just discussed a debate of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים
*Chachamim* about whether the שחיטה *shechita* of the mother works for the
child. We did not see it yet; it is in this משנה
*Mishna*. This משנה *Mishna* really revisits the implied assumption of the first
משנה *Mishna* and shows that this is a debate of רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* and the sages. So let’s take a look. השוחט את
הבהמה ומצא בה בן שמונה חי או מת *Hashochet et habehema umatza
ba ben shmona chai o met*. And somebody שחט *shachted* a בהמה
*behema* and found an eight-month-old baby that was alive, only eight months
though, or dead. או בן תשעה מת *O ben tisha met*, or
a nine-month-old that’s dead. In any of these cases, the point is
it’s either not alive or not viable. In that case, everybody agrees,
even רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, that if it’s not alive or not
viable, it’s part of the mother, and the שחיטה *shechita* of the
mother works for it. So in that case, what do you do?
קורעו ומוציא את דמו koro u'motzi es damo, *Koro umotzi et damo*.
You can eat it, the שחיטה *shechita* of the mother works, just
don’t eat the blood. It’s not different than any other limb. Any
other limb of the animal you’d have to get the blood out,
so this fetus too, you tear it, you get the blood out,
and that’s the only thing you have to worry about and even
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* agrees that the שחיטה *shechita* works. No, that’s
not a problem. We’ll talk about that. מצא בן תשעה חי *Matza
ben tisha chai*, if it was a nine-month-old and it was viable,
טעון שחיטה *taun shechita*. Then, this is רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, you
have to שחט *shecht* it. It is its own thing. The שחיטה
*shechita* of the mother does not work for it. וחייב באותו ואת
בנו *Vechayav be'oto ve'et beno*, and don’t שחט *shecht* it and the
mother on the same day because it’s its own animal and the
שחיטה *shechita* is significant for it. It’s required and significant. דברי רבי
מאיר *Divrei Rabbi Meir*, that’s רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, which is against
what we’ve been saying. וחכמים אומרים *Vachachamim omrim*, the sages say, שחיטת
אמו מטהרתו *Shechitat imo metaherato*. No, even nine-month-old and viable, the שחיטה
*shechita* of the mother works for it. רבי שמעון שזורי אומר *Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri omer*, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri says, אפילו בן חמש שנים וחורש
בשדה *Afilu ben chamesh shanim vechoreish basadeh*,
this nine-month-old viable child, you could let it grow up and become
now an old cow
and it’s plowing in the field, it’s five years old, שחיטת אמו
מטהרתו *Shechitat imo metaherato*, the שחיטה *shechita* of its mother from five
years ago says that this thing is still כשר *kosher* and now
you can go ahead and eat this animal without any
שחיטה *shechita*. What? He’s not arguing, he’s elaborating. I just said that.
Yeah, right. So it doesn’t sound like he’s arguing on the חכמים
*Chachamim*, he’s just elaborating.
No, is that only in terms of permissibility to eat or...?
We’ll talk about that in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Good question, we’ll talk about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Or
what on שבת *Shabbos*? I heard your question, we’ll talk about it
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay. השוחט... *Hashochet...* It’s a חי.
Now, let's say the, let's say
you did not שחט the mother, you just somehow did a Caesarean
section, you opened up the womb, and there was a nine month
old viable, in that case טעון שחיטה. Everybody agrees that it needs
שחיטה לפי שלא נשחטה אמו lefi shelo nishchata imo because the mother
wasn't שחט-ed. So here you have that everybody agrees when the child
is not alive or not viable, the שחיטה of the mother works
for it, but now we're saying that when it is alive and
viable, nine months old, there's a debate. רבי מאיר says the שחיטה
of the mother does not work. And what we do say is
even when the שחיטה of the mother does work, you have to
get the blood out. It's not different than any other limb. But
now we are going to talk about what about as Michael said
other things that are problems with animals, the חלב, chelev, the גיד
הנשה, gid hanasheh, and so on. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא. Amar Rabbi Elazar Amar
Rabbi Oshaya. Said רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar in the name of רבי
אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. לא הלכו בו אלא על עסקי שחיטה בלבד. Lo
hilchu bo ela al iskei shechita bilvad.
The fact that they were lenient by the fetus is only when
it comes to issues of שחיטה, not the other.
לא הלכו בו? lo hilchu bo?
They went. Okay, lenient. למעוטי מאי? Lemautei mai? What is this excluding?
למעוטי חלבו וגידו, Lemautei chelbo vegido, the fat and the גיד. gid.
So the fat and the גיד gid of the fetus actually would
be forbidden. Only the שחיטה worked. So the גמרא's going to say
one minute, חלבו דמאי? chelbo demai? Which fat? אילימא חלבו דשליל, Ilima
chelbo deshlil, if you mean the fat of the fetus, מפלג פליגי,
miflag pligi, we know that they actually debate this. דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in the ברייתא, braisa, גיד הנשה נוהג בשליל וחלבו אסור דברי
רבי מאיר, Gid hanasheh noheg beshlil vechelbo assur divrei Rabbi Meir, that
the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh is a problem by the fetus and
its fat is forbidden. That's what רבי מאיר says. רבי יהודה אומר
אינו נוהג בשליל וחלבו מותר. Rabbi Yehuda omer eino noheg beshlil vechelbo
mutar. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it does not apply to the
fetus and the fat is permissible. So as אמר רבי אלעזר אמר
רבי אושעיא amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya and we said מחלוקת
בבן תשע חי machlokes beven tesha chai that they're debating a nine
month old live animal because if it's actually not viable or not
alive, even רבי מאיר would agree it's not a problem. Their whole
debate is a nine month old viable. והלך רבי מאיר לשיטתו ורבי
יהודה לשיטתו. Vehalach Rabbi Meir lishitato veRabbi Yehuda lishitato. Each opinion is
going according to their own position. Because רבי מאיר says that the
same way it needs שחיטה, it's its own animal, and therefore its
fat and its גיד הנשה gid hanasheh is a problem. And the
rabbis say it doesn't need שחיטה, and therefore it's not its own
animal and the fat and the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh is not
a problem. What is the logic here? The logic is the following:
is that if you consider it a limb of the mother, so
the only fat that the תורה Torah forbids is the fat that's
in the mother's, you know, that's on the, you know, you know,
around the kidneys and whatever in certain locations in the mother. Here
it's fat in a different location, in this limb that happens to
be in her uterus. That's not the fat that the תורה Torah
forbade. The תורה Torah only forbade fat in certain locations. Similarly the
גיד הנשה gid hanasheh is only the גיד gid in the leg
of the animal. This isn't the גיד gid in the mother's leg,
this is the גיד gid inside this, some other sinew in some
other limb. So therefore it's not fat, it's not a גיד הנשה.
gid hanasheh. The only thing it is is that it is blood.
Blood in any limb is a problem. So if you consider it
a limb, the fat and the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh is not
a problem, the blood is. So the גמרא says you can't say
that it's only about שחיטה, we know it applies even to these
things. Okay, so the גמרא says אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. Ela
i itmar hachi itmar. Rather חלבו דגיד. chelbo degid. Maybe what you're
saying is the question about whether you can eat, not in the
case of a fetus, but in the case of a normal animal,
whether you can eat the fat that is around the גיד הנשה.
gid hanasheh. Is that forbidden fat or not? Says the גמרא, there
you can't say that that's agreed upon that that's a problem, why?
Because מפלג פליגי, miflag pligi, they also debate that. דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in the ברייתא, גיד הנשה מחטט אחריו בכל מקום שהוא וחותך
שמנו מעיקרו דברי רבי מאיר. Gid hanasheh mechateit acharav bechol makom shehu
vechotech shamno meikaro divrei Rabbi Meir. The גיד הנשה gid hanasheh again
has nothing now to do with a fetus. You have to dig
after, you have to remove all of the fat that was around
the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh and pull the fat out from its
very root, and even the fat that was around the גיד הנשה
gid hanasheh is forbidden. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says גוממו עם השופי, gomemo im hashofi, you just cut
off like the surface fat and but the fat that's deeper in
is not a problem. So anyway fat is debated. Nobody is in
agreement about that issue. So what do you mean that they only
are debating שחיטה? So אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. Ela i itmar
hachi itmar. Here it was said. אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא,
Amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya, לא הלכו בו אלא על עסקי
אכילה בלבד. lo hilchu bo ela al iskei achila bilvad. It doesn't
mean that they're only debating שחיטה, they're debating only things that relate
to eating. So the same way the rabbis say the שחיטה works,
the logic is we treat it like a limb and therefore everything
that relates to eating, the fat, גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, it's not
a problem because it's just like it's a limb. So they debate
שחיטה and everything that relates to eating that they consider it like
a limb, but not for things that are unrelated to eating. What's
unrelated to eating? So here you go Mordechai. So it says למעוטי
מאי? Lemautei mai? What does that exclude? רבעו וחורש בו. Rivo vechoresh
bo. If somebody did an act of bestiality with this fetus that
was then nine month old, was born and grew up or whatever,
or this fetus was born and nine month old fetus and the
mother was שחט-ed, grew up and then you plowed together with it
and with a donkey, you would transgress because it is considered enough
of an animal that you've plowed with a cow and a donkey
or that you've done an act of bestiality. Okay, it is not
considered for its entire life to just be a piece of meat.
For halakhic purpose, for food purposes, it's considered like it was שחט-ed
and it was part of the mother for all things that relate
to kashrut issues. But for other things it is considered to be
an animal.
What about צער בעלי חיים? tzaar baalei chayim? Never mind.
Presumably yes. Oh, that's interesting. So yeah, presumably צער בעלי חיים tzar
ba'alei chayim as well.
So stones, if it gores someone and kills them, you stone it?
It's already dead?
Yeah. Yes, that seems to be the גמרא's point that we don't
say it's already dead. We say that for כשרות kashrus purposes, the
חידוש chiddush is that the שחיטה of the mother works for it,
then within that context of כשרות, kashrus, so we see it as
a limb of the mother. For other things, we see it as
its own.
So I should expect to see אבר מן החי eiver min hachai
then is אסור, assur, but we don't.
Maybe for צער בעלי חיים tzar ba'alei chayim purposes.
But let's
say a limb fell off, that wouldn't be a problem. Got it.
Okay. So now the גמרא
says, אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, לדברי
המתירי בחלבו מתירי בדמו. l'divrei hamatiri b'chelbo matiri b'damo. The one that
says you can eat the fat says you can even eat the
blood. ודברי האוסר בחלבו אוסר בדמו. v'divrei ha'oser b'chelbo oser b'damo. If
you can't eat the fat, you can't eat the blood. Which is
against what we said before. Before we said the blood is a
problem according to everyone. ורבי יוחנן אמר, v'Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said, אף לדברי המתירי בחלבו, af l'divrei hamatiri b'chelbo, even
if the fat is okay, אוסר בדמו, oser b'damo, you can't eat
the blood, because even if it's just a limb, the blood in
every limb is a problem. So, איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש. eitivei
Rabbi Yochanan l'Resh Lakish. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asked a קושיא
kushya to ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. Our משנה says, קורעו ומוציא את
דמו, that even that when it says by the non-viable or the
dead fetus, you have to get the blood out. And that's a
case that even רבי מאיר says is considered a limb and the
fat isn't a problem, and nevertheless it says you have to get
out the blood. So the גמרא says, אמר רב זירא, amar Rav
Zeira, so says רב זירא, Rav Zeira, לומר שאין ענו כרת. lomar
she'ein eno kareis. When ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said the blood isn't
a problem, he didn't mean the blood wasn't a problem. What he
meant, he meant it's not as, it's not the blood that you
get כרת kareis for. You only get כרת kareis for the blood
that is considered the lifeblood, the blood that comes out when you
שחט it. Okay, but blood that's absorbed within the limbs, like when
we salt the meat to get out the blood, that is not
blood you would get כרת kareis for. That's just blood that's prohibited
by a לאו, lav, it's not the lifeblood. So what ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish was saying is of course you can't eat the blood.
He's not going to argue on the logic that even if it's
a limb, the blood is still a problem. But what he's saying
is, it's true, it's a limb and the blood is a problem.
My point, says ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, is that even if you
were to שחט this fetus and the blood would come squirting out,
it wouldn't be considered lifeblood. You wouldn't get כרת kareis for it.
It's just blood of a limb. So that was his point. Okay.
So let's take a look what the גמרא now does with this.
So the גמרא says, למאן קאמר, l'man ka'amar, one minute. Who are
you saying that according to the one who says it's permissible? רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the שחיטה of
the mother works for the infant, and therefore the חלב chelev is
permissible, the גיד gid is permissible of this, and you're saying the
blood is also at least not כרת. kareis. So one minute. לא
יהיה אלא דם התמציות. lo yehei ela dam hatamtzis. Even if it's
just blood of the actual meat itself, meaning the remnant blood, not
the blood of, not the lifeblood, which normally we say you don't
get כרת, kareis, but nevertheless רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you get
כרת kareis even for that blood. So how can you say this
is just a limb and therefore there's no כרת kareis in the
blood? You're saying that according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he's the
one that says the שחיטה works, and he says even the blood
of limbs you get כרת kareis for. How do you know? דתניא,
d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, דם התמציות בלא תעשה, dam hatamtzis
b'lo sa'aseh, the blood of like that's that remains that's not the
lifeblood is a negative prohibition, but not כרת. kareis. רבי יהודה אומר
בכרת, Rabbi Yehuda omer b'kareis, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says even that
blood gets כרת. kareis. So how can you say this blood you
don't get כרת kareis for? תרגמה רב יוסף בריה דרב סלא חסידא
קמיה דרב פפא. Targema Rav Yosef breih d'Rav Salla Chasida kamey d'Rav
Pappa. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, the son of רב פפא,
Rav Pappa, אית ליה לרבי יהודה דם וכל דם. is lei l'Rabbi
Yehuda dam v'chol dam. How does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda know you
get כרת kareis for the blood that's not the lifeblood? Because because
the פסוק pasuk says וכל דם לא תאכלו, v'chol dam lo socheilu,
all blood, which means not only the lifeblood, even the non-lifeblood. But
that is because it's an extension of the concept of the lifeblood.
It is only relevant when there is lifeblood to an animal. כל
היכא דמחייב אדם הנפש, kol heicha d'mechayev adam hanefesh, when you could
get
כרת, kareis you get כרת kareis even for the blood that's in
the limb. וכל היכא דלא מחייב אדם נפש, v'kol heicha d'lo mechayev
adam nefesh, when you can't get כרת kareis for the lifeblood because
there is no lifeblood, in this fetus, there's no lifeblood. Even if
you were to שחט it, it's considered like just a limb. So
there's no lifeblood in this fetus. So לא מחייב אדם התמציות, lo
mechayev adam hatamtzis, you don't get כרת kareis
even for the blood of the limb. So now we understand what
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish was saying. Now actually it's an interesting point.
He's saying, look, I understand you שחט the mother, this is considered
a limb, the חלב chelev isn't forbidden, the גיד gid isn't forbidden.
I understand though that there still is blood and the blood is
forbidden. That's what our משנה says. But he says, I want to
tell you something. That blood even according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that says you normally get כרת kareis. for blood in limbs, for
this blood in this limb, this fetus, you don't get כרת. kareis
Why? Because you only get כרת kareis for blood in limbs when
it relates to lifeblood. And for this fetus, although interestingly the mother
had lifeblood and the whole reason you're eating the fetus is because
it was part of the mother, so you could've said it's the
same thing, but no, here we look at the fetus in its
own terms. And since the fetus doesn't have lifeblood because the שחיטה
works, the blood in the limb you also don't get כרת for.
Okay, now let's just read one more thing now that we're sort
of figuring out that this thing is considered שחט and a limb
for food purposes but not for other purposes, we're going to have
some interesting questions about what are those other purposes. Okay. איבעיא להו,
Iba'u lehu, they asked the question: מהו לפדות בבן פקועה? mahu lifdot
b'ben pakua? You have this בן פקועה. ben pakua Now, if you
have a firstborn of a donkey, you can redeem it with a
sheep, even if the sheep is of lesser value. So you have
a בן פקועה ben pakua of a sheep, we're normally assuming a
calf. Is it considered enough of a sheep? Remember, for food purposes
it's food. For other purposes, it's an animal. So here it is,
it's a sheep, is it enough of a sheep that you can
redeem your firstborn donkey with it? Why not? What's the
issue? אליבא דרבי מאיר לא תיבעי, Aliba d'Rabbi Meir lo tibei, according
to רבי מאיר there's no question it works, דכיון דאמר טעון שחיטה,
d'keivan d'amar taun shchita, since he says you have to שחט it,
שה מעליא הוא, seh ma'alyahu, of course it's a sheep. כי תיבעי
לך, Ki tibei lach, what's the question אליבא דרבנן, aliba d'Rabanan, the
רבנן, דאמרי שחיטת אמו מטהרתו, d'amri shchitat imo metaherato,
the שחיטה of the mother works for it? מאי, Mai, what do
we say? כיון דאמר שחיטת אמו מטהרתו, Keivan d'amar shchitat imo metaherato,
the שחיטה of the mother works for it, כבשר בדיקולא דמי, k'basar
b'dikula dami, it's like meat in a pot, it's just meat, which
seems to be sort of like arguing on the earlier point, maybe
for all purposes we just look at it like meat? או דילמא,
O dilma, or do we say, because you gotta love
this line, כיון דרהיט ואזיל ורהיט ואתי, keivan d'rahit v'azil v'rahit v'ati,
since it runs, it runs back and forth, שה קרינא ביה, seh
karina beih, we can't just call it meat, it actually is running
around in the yard, so we'll call it a sheep. What? Exactly.
So מר זוטרא אמר אין פודים, Mar Zutra amar ein podin, מר
זוטרא Mar Zutra says you can't redeem. רב ששת אמר פודים, Rav
Sheshet amar podin, רב ששת Rav Sheshet says you can. אמר ליה
רב אשי למר זוטרא, Amar leh Rav Ashi l'Mar Zutra, I'm sorry,
so רב אשי Rav Ashi said to מר זוטרא, Mar Zutra, מאי
דעתך, mai daitach, what's your logic that you think that you can't
redeem? דגמרת שה שה מפסחים, D'gamrat seh seh m'psachim, you learn a
גזירה שוה gezeirah shava שה שה seh seh from the קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, and the same way this בן פקועה ben pakua can't
work for קרבן פסח Korban Pesach because it's already שחוט, shechted, you
can't bring something that's already שחוט shechted as a קרבן, korban, so
therefore you can't use it for a פדיון pidyon because of a
גזירה שוה. gezeirah shava. One minute. אי מה להלן זכר תמים ובן
שנה, Ei ma l'halan zachar tamim u'ven shanah,
you don't really compare to קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach has to be male, unblemished, one year old. אף כאן, Af
kan, will you say when you redeem your donkey the sheep has
to be זכר תמים ובן שנה? zachar tamim u'ven shanah? So we
don't say those things, so you can't exclude it because it's not
enough like a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So מאי אהני, mai ahani,
so he says תפדה תפדה ריבה. tifdeh tifdeh ribah.
So how come we don't make that? Because we say the it
said you shall redeem it, that's to say however you redeem it,
any type of sheep works. ואי תפדה תפדה ריבה, V'i tifdeh tifdeh
ribah, and once you're saying it doesn't have to be exactly like
the sheep of a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, אפילו כל מילי נמי,
afilu kol mili nami,
then even this type of בן פקועה ben pakua should work. So
I don't see why you think a בן פקועה won't work. So
the answer back is no, אם כן, im ken, שה שה מאי
אהני לך? seh seh mai ahani lach?
If that's true, then שה שה seh seh we can't just say
תפדה תפדה ריבה. tifdeh tifdeh ribah. There is for some purpose there's
a גזירה שוה gezeirah shava to connect to the קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. So not for all things, not for most things, but at
least to exclude this case of a בן פקועה that you can't
use. So I want to make a point, the way the גמרא
frames the question initially sounded like it was ignoring the earlier discussions,
sounded like it says even for non-food purposes we'll consider this to
be like a piece of meat, right? And then maybe you can't
redeem. In the end, the only reason the גמרא says you can't
use it to redeem would be because of some גזירה שוה gezeirah
shava to קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. It wasn't exactly like a קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. So in the end the גמרא is being consistent,
and it's saying for food purposes it's like a limb and it's
like a piece of meat, for non-food purposes it's an animal, for
bestiality, for you know, plowing an ox and a donkey, for redeeming,
the only possibility is here and there it might be excluded because
of its special status. But fundamentally it's not for other purposes, it's
not meat, for other purposes it is an animal.